Finding Aid for Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies, University of Michigan Records
Bentley Historical Library
Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies, University of Michigan Records
1961-1992
1961-1986
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies.
9843 Bimu/2
2.7 linear feet
A cross-disciplinary center at the University of Michigan for the study of the languages, history, culture and contemporary society of South and Southeast Asia, records document the administration of the Center and some of the programs and research activities it sponsored.
The records were transferred by the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies in1997 (Donor no. 4715 ).
The collection is open for research.
The Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies (CSSEAS) was founded in 1961 with a grant from the Ford Foundation as part of a new American effort following World War II to study Asian languages, history and cultures. In 1959 the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) had proposed the expansion of "area studies" at the University of Michigan. This proposal included the establishment of four "area centers": the Center for Chinese Studies, the Center for Russian and Eastern European Studies, the Center for Near and Middle Eastern Studies as well as CSSEAS, using the Center for Japanese Studies as a model. Special emphasis was placed on the mastery of foreign languages and field research abroad. CSSEAS soon became a distinguished "area center," an institution within the American university system supporting interdisciplinary study on a specific cultural and geographic region of the world.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s CSSEAS sponsored and hosted many conferences and summer programs, bringing together scholars, students and South and Southeast Asians from around the world. Associates are drawn from the faculty and students of existing University of Michigan departments and programs, especially history, political science, anthropology and linguistics to work together and share ideas about South and Southeast Asian topics. Many students do dual concentrations in South and Southeast Asian studies and other subjects, especially business and linguistics. In 1993 CSSEAS became part of the International Institute, which administers the university's area centers.
In 1999, two new independent units emerged from the Center: the Center for South Asian Studies and the Center for Southeast Asian Studies.
Directors of the Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies
1960-1962 Richard Park
1962-1965 L.A. Peter Gosling
1965 Russell Fitfield (Acting)
1966-1968 Gayl D. Ness
1969-1971 John H. Broomfield
1971-1972 L.A. Peter Gosling
1972-1975 Alton Lewis Becker
1975-1977 Thomas R. Trautmann
1977-1980 L.A. Peter Gosling
1980-1983 Madhav Deshpande
1983-1987 Karl L. Hutterer
1987-1989 Rhoads Murphey
1989-1992 Victor B. Lieberman
1992-1995 Nicholas B. Dirks
1995-1998 Hemalata Dandekar
Directors of the Center for Southeast Asian Studies
1998-2005 Judith Omans Becker
2006-2008 Linda Lim
2008-2009 Allen Hicken (Interim)
2009 Linda Lim
2010-2013 Allen Hicken
2013- Christi-Anne Castro
Directors of the Center for South Asian Studies
1998-2000 Pradeep Chhibber
2000-2003 Sumathi Ramaswamy (Interim)
2003-2007 Sumathi Ramaswamy
2007-2009 William Glover
2010-2011 Juan Cole
2012- Farina Mir
The record group is divided into three series: Administrative Records, Funding and Programs and Conferences.
The Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies record group dates from the 1960s to the 1990s, but is strongest for the 1960s and 1970s. There are many gaps in the record group, and little information is available regarding the Center's establishment or a general overview of the Center's activities. Even so, there is much material on some Center activities, especially conferences and summer programs.
Area studies -- Michigan.; Asia, Southeastern -- Study and teaching.; Orientalists -- Michigan.; South Asia -- Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Center for South and Southeast Asian Studies.
- Administrative Records
  Administrative Records consists of approximately 1.5 linear feet of material and is divided into two subseries, the first of which is entitled Staff Files. The Staff Files contain the Directors' Correspondence for the late 1960s, most of the 1970s and the early 1980s, information on the Center's associates, a few Library files regarding the Center's holdings in the Graduate Library's Asia Library, and Center correspondence with other Southeast Asian studies institutes. The second subseries of Topical Files is organized alphabetically and documents Center projects, studies groups, mailings and information on specific areas of South and Southeast Asian study.
  - Staff Files
    - Director's Correspondence
      - Gayl Ness, 1968 (Box 1)
      - John Broomfield, 1969 (Box 1)
      - L. A. P. Gosling
        - 1971-1974 (Box 1)
        - 1977 (Box 1)
        - 1978 (Box 1)
        - 1979 (Box 1)
        - 1980 (Box 1)
      - Madhav Deshpande (South Asia), 1980-1982 (Box 1)
      - Aram Yengoyan (Southeast Asia), 1980 (Box 1)
      - Area Centers Directors Meetings, 1965-1974 (Box 1)
    - Center Correspondence
      - East-West Center, 1966-1974 (Box 1)
      - Kyoto University, Japan, Center for Southeast Asian Studies, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
      - Philippine-American Association, 1967 (Box 1)
      - Singapore Institute of Southeast Asian Studies, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
      - South Asia General, 1960s (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - Associates Records
      - Associates Biographical Data/Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
      - Staff Records, 1964-1970 (Box 1)
      - Personnel, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Library Records
      - Library Budget, 1967 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Asian Studies Program Undergraduate (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Agenda and Minutes, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
    - Gandhi Centennial Committee, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Information on Philippine Martial Law, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Languages
      - South Asia Language Teaching, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Mailings and Newsletters, 1960s-1970s (Box 2)
    - Michigan Teachers in Asian Studies 1991, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Microfilming papers of Manuel Quezon, 1965-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naropa Institute, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Program Evaluation Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
    - Ramayana Mini-Course, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Research Opportunities at the National Archives of Malaysia, by Tom Willer [4 pp., n.d.] (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Mailings Received, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Business
      - Number 1 & 2, Spring/Summer, 1984 (Box 2)
      - Number 2, Fall 1984 (Box 2)
      - Number 3, Winter 1985 (Box 2)
      - Number 4, Spring 1985 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Reader Project, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Regional Council, Association for Asian Studies, Programs in Southeast Asian Studies, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia Visiting Scholar, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Studies Groups
      - Burma Studies Group, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Indonesia Studies Group, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - University Evaluation and Planning, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Funding
  Funding consists of less than 0.5 linear feet of material regarding the various sources from which the center receives funding, including the Ford Foundation, the National Defense Education Act, Foreign Language and Area Studies fellowships and Department of Education grants. The material spans the 1960s through the 1990s and is organized alphabetically.
  - Fellowships, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Grant
    - Correspondence
      - 1961-1965 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1964-1975 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Area Fellowship Program, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - Funding Sources, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - International Education Act, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Jacobson Report, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - National Defense Education Act Language and Area, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - National Defense Foreign Language Fellowships, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Proposal, South Asian Theatrical Forms, 1973 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Survey, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Proposal for Department of Education Grant, 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Proposal for Department of Education Grant, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
  - Southeast Asia Regional Council, Association for Asian Studies, Sources of Funding for Individual Southeast Asia Specialists, January 1974 (Box 2)
- Programs and Conferences
  Programs and Conferences consists of less than 1 linear foot of material divided in half into two groups. The first is arranged alphabetically and contains material on various Center sponsored seminars, conferences and summer programs, including the Committee on Institutional Cooperation Summer Program in Southeast Asian Languages and Literature in the early 1970s. The second half consists entirely of material relating to the Southeast Asian Studies Summer Institute (SEASSI), an annual summer program concentrating on Southeast Asian languages and literature organized by a partnership of universities with Southeast Asian studies programs. Originally called the Indonesian Studies Summer Institute, SEASSI was created in 1983 to expand the summer program's area of study to include all of Southeast Asia. It is sponsored by the Southeast Asian Regional Council of the Association for Asian Studies (an organization composed of several Southeast Asian studies centers and of which CSSEAS is an active member) and was hosted by CSSEAS at the University of Michigan in 1984 and 1985.
  - Austronesian Conference, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Borobudur Conference, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Center Sponsored Cultural Events, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Conferences, February-March 1976 (Box 3)
  - Gamelan Javanese Musical Set, 1965-1969; 1978 (Box 3)
  - Maharashtra Conference, April 1973 (Box 3)
  - Nepal Symposium and Seminar, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Elman R. Service Conference, Ecology and Cultural Evolution in the Tropics, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Symbolic Forms and Systems Conference, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Summer Programs
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation Summer Program in Southeast Asian Language and Literature
      - University of Michigan, 1970 (Box 3)
      - University of Wisconsin, 1971 (Box 3)
      - University of Chicago, 1972 (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Summer Institute and Proposal, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Southeast Asian Studies Summer Institute (SEASSI)
      - Correspondence, Flyers and Newsletters
        - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
        - 1983 (Box 3)
        - 1984 (Box 3)
        - 1985 (Box 3)
        - 1986 (Box 3)
        - 1987 (Box 3)
      - External Funding, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Fourth Eastern Conference on Austronesian Languages (ECAL-IV), 1985 (Box 3)
      - Fulbright Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Luce Fellowships, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - Studies Groups
        - Burma (Box 3)
        - Indonesia (Box 3)
        - Malaysia/Singapore/Brunei (Box 3)
        - Thai/Laos/Cambodia (Box 3)
        - Vietnam (Box 3)